Guide to the Harrison of Paris Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Harrison of Paris records
1930-1979
1930-1934
YCAL MSS 148
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.05
(4 boxes)
The Harrison of Paris records document the output of the short-lived fine press and include drafts of texts, setting copy, correspondence, advertisements, catalogs, and clippings. The records described here were culled from the papers of Monroe Wheeler, co-founder of the press. These are presumed to be the most complete group of records with direct provenance from the original press.
Harrison of Paris
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received with the Glenway Wescott Papers and the Monroe Wheeler Papers, purchase from Monroe Wheeler, 1988, with later purchase and gift from Anatole Pohorilenko, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Other manuscript materials relating to writings by Glenway Wescott published by Harrison of Paris can be found in the Glenway Wescott Papers [YCAL MSS 134].
HARRISON OF PARIS
Harrison of Paris was a fine press run by Barbara Harrison [later Wescott] and Monroe Wheeler. Established in Paris in 1930, it took as its goal the production of limited editions of belle-lettres texts, principally contemporary. (Monroe Wheeler had previously done very small editions in the 1920s, under the imprint "Manikin".) Over five years, the press produced 13 titles, including two by Glenway Wescott.
In 1934, shortly before the marriage of Barbara Harrison to Glenway Wescott's younger brother, Lloyd, the press was relocated to New York, where it brought out a final title, Katherine Anne Porter's Hacienda.
Though the production stopped in 1934, Harrison of Paris continued to influence other fine presses which followed its style. A complete listing of its output follows: 1930 Venus and Adonis by William Shakespeare The Wild West by Bret Harte, with illustrations by Pierre Falké A Sketch of my Life by Thomas Mann The Babe's Bed by Glenway Wescott 1931 Fables of Aesop translated by Sir Roger L'Estrange, with illustrations by Alexander Calder Carmen and Letters from Spain by Prosper Merimée, with illustrations by Maurice Barraud The Death of Madame by the Comtesse de Lafayette, translated by Monroe Wheeler A Gentle Spirit by Fyodor Dostoevsky, translated by C. Garnett, with illustrations by Christian Bérard Childe Harolde's Pilgrimage by Lord Byron, with illustrations by Sir Francis Rose A Calendar of Saints for Unbelievers by Glenway Wescott, with illustrations by Pavel Tchelitchew 1932 A Typographical Commonplace Book 1933 Katherine Anne Porter's French Song-Book 1934 Hacienda by Katherine Anne Porter, 1934
Scope and Contents
The Harrison of Paris records document the output of the short-lived fine press and include drafts of texts, setting copy, correspondence, advertisements, catalogs, and clippings. The material covers the years 1930-1979, with the bulk of items dating from the period the press was active, 1930-34. The records described here were culled from the papers of Monroe Wheeler, co-founder of the press. These are presumed to be the most complete group of records with direct provenance from the original press.
The records are housed in 3 boxes and are organized into three series: I. Publications; II. Correspondence; and III. Other Material. Box 9 contains oversize material from Series III.
Series I, Publications, contains 1930s period material relating to eight publications. Most titles are represented by sketches of title pages, specimen pages and prospectuses. The most complete records are for Death of Madame (the text of Monroe Wheeler's translation) and A Typographical Commonplace Book (a set of proof page variants with original texts). Other titles are represented by later records attesting to their reprinting, including an unauthorized copy of Venus and Adonis.
Also present are preparatory materials for two volumes which were never completed by the press (or at least publicly presented): "For My Father", a memoir by Barbara Harrison Wescott and an unidentified book of aphorisms which may have been intended as a second commonplace book.
Series II, Correspondence, contains mostly letters from printers about agreements and the status of projects. There are also letters from Maurice Barraud, who illustrated Carmen and Letters from Spain. The series concludes with a group of general financial and legal correspondence concerning the dissolution of the company and a group of bills for typesetting, printing, and binding. [Related correspondence can be found in the Monroe Wheeler Papers (YCAL MSS 136)]
Series III, Other Material, consists principally of items from the workings of the press itself (advertisements, catalogs, clippings and scrapbooks) and subsequent documentation of the history of the press (auction and booksellers' catalogs and exhibition material). Among the other items here are a setting copy of an invitation to an exhibition of photographs by George Platt Lynes, a typescript of a poem by Elizabeth Madox Roberts, and two copies of the 1932 Harrison of Paris catalog with ink sketches by an unidentified artist.
Small presses -- United States; Wescott, Barbara Harrison; Wheeler, Monroe, 1899-1988; Harrison of Paris
- Publications, 1930-1979; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  - The Babe's Bed by Glenway Wescott
    - Photocopy of printed text, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Calendar of Saints for Unbelievers by Glenway Wescott
    - Title page: sketches and setting page (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Specimen pages, 1978 Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carmen and Letters from Spain by Prosper Merimée
    - Page proof, corrected - title page only, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Childe Harold's Pilgrimage by Lord Byron
    - Page proof - title page only, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Specimen pages, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Death of Madame by the Comtesse de Lafayette
    - Translation by Monroe Wheeler, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fables of Aesop
    - Sketch of title page, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paper knives, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Clippings re: Dover reprint, 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Citation of book in undentified article (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "For My Father" by Barbara Harrison Wescott
    - Setting copy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sketches and page proofs, ca. 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - List of names (of recipients?), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hacienda by Katherine Anne Porter
    - Prospectus, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Sample printed page, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Certificate of copyright registration, 1934 Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - United States distributor's purchase order, 1939 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Katherine Anne Porter's French Song-Book
    - Prospectus, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Sketch of title page, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - A Typographical Commonplace Book
    - Setting pages, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Proof page variants with original texts, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 23-56)
    - Advertisement draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Specimen list, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Specimen pages, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Venus and Adonis by William Shakespeare
    - Copy of unauthorized reprint, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Article by Horace Hart on unauthorized reprint, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Unidentified book of aphorisms (Second Commonplace Book?)
    - Sketches and proofs (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Correspondence, 1930-1951; Series II; 0.21; (.5 box)
  - Barraud, Maurice, 1931-32 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Cassel & Company, 1930 Mar 20 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Editiones Officina Bodoni [Hans Mardersteig], 1932 Sep 15 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - The Haddon Craftsmen, 1934 Dec 18 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - "Jack" from Frank A. Munsey Company, 1935 Sep 30 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Kunstverlag Wolfrum, 1933 Apr 22 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - W. Collins Sons & Co., 1935 Jun 27 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Westwood Bookstore, 1948, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - General financial and legal correspondence, 1939-41 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Bills for typesetting, printing and binding, 1930-34 (Box 3, Folder 72)
- Other Material, 1930-1978; Series III; 0.21; (.5 box)
  - Address labels, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Advertisment drafts and proofs, ca. 1931-33 (Box 3, Folder 74-77)
  - Auction and booksellers' listings of Harrison of Paris books, 1969-78 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Book Club of California announcement of exhibition, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Catalog, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Catalog, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Catalog, galley proof, corrected, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Catalog, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Catalog with sketches by unidentified artist, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Catalog, ca. 1934 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Clippings, 1930-35, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 86-88)
  - Display label, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Exhibition at the American Library in Paris, booklet and clipping, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Invitation to exhibition of photographs by George Platt Lynes, setting copy, 1932 Mar (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - List of abbreviations of sized of books, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - List of Harrison of Paris publications, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - List of possible titles for projects, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Modern bookbinding exhibition at Columbia University, invitation and catalog, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Notebook of aphorisms copied by Barbara Harrison Wescott, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Order slip, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Issue of Philobiblon containing supplement advertising Harrison of Paris publications, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Projected costs and returns for A Typographical Commonplace Book and A Calendar of Saints for Unbelievers (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Revised book price list, 1948 Oct (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Scrapbooks, 1930-35
  - Specimen of Glaslan paper, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Specimen page from American Book-Stratford Press, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Stationery, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - "Summer is Ended" by Elizabeth Madox Roberts, typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 104)
- Oversize, 1930-1935; 1; (1 box)
  - Scrapbooks (in Series III), 1930-35 (Box 4, Folder 105-106)